General Electric Company Records 5331
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
General Electric Company Records
1938-1967
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
General Electric Company
5331
2.67 cubic feet
2.7 linear ft.
Records (documents).
U.S. NLRB decision on General Electric and International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers 1960 Contract Negotiations.
5599272
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, November 06, 2012
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 11, 2019
Biographical / Historical
At the time of these negotiations, General Electric Company was the fourth largest industrial corporation in the United States. It manufactured over 200,000 individual products ranging from toasters to turbines.
Approximately 120,000 of its 250,000 employees were represented by labor organizations. There were no nationally certified unions or multi-plant units in the company, each union being represented on a plant by plant basis. The company conducted national bargaining with three of the one hundred odd unions representing it's workers, these being the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America, (UE), the Pattern Makers League of North America, and the International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers, (IUE). The latter union was certified as bargaining agent for approximately 70,000 G.E. employees in 1950 as a result of the expulsion of the UE from the Congress of Industrial Organizations for alleged communist activities. One year contracts were successfully negotiated between the company and the IUE between 1950 and 1955. In 1955 the parties entered into a five year agreement which included a wage escalator clause and provisions for a reopening of the contract in 1958 on the question of employment security. The contract terms set forth by the company in the 1955 agreement were apparently regretted during the period of economic decline that began in 1957. This attitude was reflected in the hard economic line taken by the company in the 1958 bargaining session, which ended in a stalemate. The stage was thus set for the 1960 contract negotiations, the company intending to keep costs down while the union hoped to recoup the losses it suffered in 1958.
THE 1960 NEGOTIATIONS
Preparations for the negotiations commenced at meetings between company and union officials on January 26, April 1 and April 26 at which time the company supplied the union with information and materials deemed vital to the impending negotiations. It was agreed at these meetings that negotiations of the employment security issue would open on June 13, approximately two months before the contract date for the opening of formal negotiations. The union presented the full slate of its demands at the June 13 meeting and requested that full negoitations commence at an earlier date than scheduled.
Formal negotiations between the parties opened on July 19 and continued through 45 meetings, ending on October 22, after a three week strike. The I.U.E. filed charges against the company before the National Labor Relations Board on September 21, October 4, October 14, 1960 and March 16, 1961 charging the company with unfair labor practices under sections 8(a) 1, 3 and 5, and sections 2 (6) and (7) of the National Labor Relations Act.
The specific charges against the company under Section 8 (a) (7) (to interfere with, restrain or coerce employees in the exercise of the rights guaranteed in Section 7), stemmed from the company's policy of bargaining with local units in derogation of the union's status as national bargaining agent. Section 8 (a) (5) (to refuse to bargain collectively with representatives of the employees) was allegedly violated by the company's refusal to supply vacation and pension information to the union during the course of negotiations. Section 8 (a) (3) (discrimination in regard to hire or tenure of employment or any term or conditions of employment to encourage or discourage membership in any labor organization) was con- sidered to have been violated when the employer refused to reinstate twenty workers who had been replaced during the strike. These violations were incurred by the employer as defined under sections 2 (6) and (7) of the N.L.R.A.
On April 1, 1963 N.L.R.B. trial Examiner Arthur Leff issued an intermediate report finding the company guilty of the aforementioned violations and recommended that the company cease and desist from such further activities. In addition to specific charges, the examiner criticized the company's overall approach to and conduct of bargaining. In finding such, he attached the cease and desist order to the bargaining tactics, thereby ruling that the Bulwaristic strategy was not in the interest of true collective bargaining. The ruling of the trial examiner was upheld by a majority decision of the NLRB in its decision on December 6, 1964.
Scope and Contents
U.S. NLRB decision on General Electric and International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers 1960 Contract Negotiations.
Included are transcripts of the proceedings before the trial examiner and the board; materials detailing the prosecution of the case; the company's defense; and a General Electric information kit.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /3017: Abraham Cohen "Coordinated Bargaining at General Electric: An Analysis" Dissertation Supporting Documentation 5886: GE "Leaders Discussion Guide to HOBSO" 6081 mf: GE (Schenectady, NY) Publication "Works News" on Microfilm
Arrangement
Series Company's defense
Series General Electric information kit
Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Electric industry workers -- United States; Electric industry workers -- Labor unions -- United States; United States. National Labor Relations Board.; General Electric Company; United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America.; International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers.
5599272
- The General Counsel's Brief to the Trial Examiner (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  321 pp.
- Appendices to the General Counsel's Brief to the trial examiner (Box 1, Folder 2)
  87 pp.
- General Counsel's Reply Brief to the Trial Examiner (Box 1, Folder 3)
  52 pp.
- Intermediate Report (decision of the trial examiner) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  113 pp. 4 copies
- General Counsel's Brief in Support of Exceptions and in Support of the Intermediate Report (Box 1, Folder 5)
  49 pp.
- Decision and Order of the National Labor Relations Board (Box 1, Folder 6)
  11 pp. 4 copies
- Press release of the NLRB announcing the decision (Box 1, Folder 7)
  8 pp.
- Series Company's defense
  - Respondent's Brief for Trial Examiner: Part I. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    217 pp.
  - Respondent's Brief for Trial examiner: Part 11. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    100 pp.
  - Respondent's Reply Brief for Trial Examiner (Box 1, Folder 10)
    87 pp. 2 copies
  - Respondent's Exceptions to the Intermediate Report (Box 1, Folder 11)
    78 pp. 2 copies
  - Respondent's Brief in Support of its exceptions to the Intermediate Report (Box 1, Folder 12)
    24 pp.
- Series General Electric information kit
  - General Electric's press release (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Issued on December 16 at Press Conference in Washington and New York
  - Background summary and evaluation of NLRB decision. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Editorial comment in New York press and other Newspapers. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - ER News story, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Dated December 21, 1964.
  - Sample employee communication following announcement of the NLRB decision. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Background materials covering events leading up to NLRB decision announced on December 16, 1964. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Excess Profits Tax - Book No. 11 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- How Big is Our Job?, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- GE-Annual Report: 1946, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Stabilization of Industry by Gerard Swope, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- GE Publications (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Camp Nola (Box 2, Folder 15)
- GE--Annual Reports: [1938, 1939, 1941, 1943-1945], 1938-1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- something to Read Book 18 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- General Electric - Employee Relations News Letter, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Educational Facilities for Employees of the General Electric Company Schenectady Works (Box 2, Folder 11)
- GE - Employee Relations News Letter, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Employee Communication: Executive Summary (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Charles Edward Wilson, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Story of X-ray (Box 2, Folder 7)
- General Electric Company Research Laboratory - No. 953, 1100 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Research and Innovation (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Story of Lightning (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Story of GE Research (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Story of Steinmetz (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Where does the money go (Box 2, Folder 12)
- GE Communicator, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Employee Communication in Connection with 1966: General Electric negotiations, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- GE - Job Evaluation, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- GE - Salary Evaluation, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Apprentice Training Courses Schenectady Works (Box 2, Folder 36)
- General Electric Pension Plans, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Constitution and By-Laws, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- What about a Fourth Round of Wage Increases?, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Employees Annual Suggestion Report, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Tentative New Departure, Bristol: Supervisory Education and Training Program, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Flight Propulsion Division - Evendale Plant Newscaler, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Careers in the Electrical Industry (Box 2, Folder 29)
- General Electric Round Table: Guide for Supervisors (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Supervisor's Guide to General Electric Job Information (Box 2, Folder 27)
- You and General Electric: A handbook (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Supervisor's Handbook on Employee Relations (Box 2, Folder 25)
- GE - Employee Relations News Letter (1956-1958, 1960), 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- GE - Employee Relations News Letter, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- GE - Employee Relations News Letter, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Safety Pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 32)
- General Electric News - Evendale Plant, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Schenectady News, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- General Electric News: 1957-1960 [no year/vol. is complete] (Box 3, Folder 1)